M. L. Parrish Collection of Victorian Novelists, 1806-1958 (bulk 1830s-1930s ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
Additional information on the collection is located at: http://www.princeton.edu/~ferguson/h-tor-z.html (scroll down to the section on "Victorian Novelists")
For details on the growth of the Parrish collection between 1944 and 1956 refer to: Alexander D. Wainwright, "The Morris L. Parrish Collection of Victorian Novelists: A Summary Report and an Introduction," in the Princeton University Library Chronicle XVII, (Winter, 1956) pp. 59-67. The Princeton University Library Chronicle devoted two entire issues to this collection (VIII, 1, November 1946 and XVII, 2, Winter 1956).
For Lewis Carroll photograph holdings, see Roger Taylor and Edward Wakeling, Lewis Carroll Photographer: The Princeton University Library Albums (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 2002).
"A Summary Report and an Introduction," Alexander D. Wainwright, The Princeton University Library Chronicle (Volume XVII, Number 2, Winter 1956, pp. 59-67).
Brussel, I. R. (Isidore Rosenbaum), 1895- -- Correspondence.; Hargreaves, Alice Pleasance Liddell, 1852-1934 -- Photographs.; Randall, David A. (David Anton), 1905-1975 -- Correspondence.; Sadleir, Michael, 1888-1957 -- Correspondence.; Wilson, Carroll A. (Carroll Atwood), 1886-1947 -- Correspondence.; Ainsworth, William Harrison, 1805-1882.; Barrie, J. M.(James Matthew), 1860-1937.; Black, William, 1841-1898.; Braddon, M. E.(Mary Elizabeth), 1835-1915.; Brontë, Charlotte, 1816-1855.; Brontë, Emily, 1818-1848.; Brontë, Anne, 1820-1849.; Brontë, Patrick Branwell, 1817-1848.; Browne, Hablot Knight, 1815-1882.; Carroll, Lewis, 1832-1898.; Collins, Wilkie, 1824-1889.; Craik, Dinah Maria Mulock, 1826-1887.; Dickens, Charles,1812-1870.; Disraeli, Benjamin,Earl of Beaconsfield, 1804-1881.; Du Maurier, George, 1834-1896.; Eliot, George, 1819-1880.; Gaskell, Elizabeth Cleghorn, 1810-1865.; Hardy, Thomas, 1840-1928.; Holiday, Henry, 1839-1927.; Hughes, Thomas, 1822-1896.; Kingsley, Charles, 1819-1875.; Lever, Charles James, 1806-1872.; Lytton, Edward Bulwer Lytton,Baron, 1803-1873.; Meredith, George, 1828-1909.; Ouida, 1839-1908.; Reade, Charles, 1814-1884.; Scott, Walter,Sir, 1771-1832.; Stevenson, Robert Louis, 1850-1894.; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863.; Thirkell, Angela Mackail, 1890-1961.; Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882.; Trollope, Thomas Adolphus, 1810-1892.; Trollope, Frances Eleanor, d. 1913.; Trollope, Frances Milton, 1780-1863.; Trollope, Theodosia Garrow, 1825-1865.; Wood, Henry,Mrs., d1814-1887.; Yonge, Charlotte Mary, 1823-1901.; Book collecting -- United States -- 20th century.; Booksellers and bookselling -- England -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; English literature -- 19th century.; Illustrators -- England -- 19th century -- Drawings.; Novelists, English -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Novelists, English -- 19th century -- Manuscripts.; Women novelists, English -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Women novelists, English -- 19th century -- Manuscripts.; Fiction -- 19th century.; Correspondence -- 19th century.; Drafts (preliminary versions) -- 19th century.; Drawings -- 19th century.; Manuscripts (for publication) -- 19th century.; Photoprints -- 19th century.; Art history; Book history and arts; British literature
- Series 1: Artwork and Manuscripts, 1700-2999; 13 boxes
  Consists of manuscripts, both bound and unbound, mostly oversize, and artwork/ephemera housed in a variety of oversize containers.
  The artwork is arranged alphabetically, for the most part, by artist, and stored in boxes on shelves 1-6; the bound manuscripts are shown here in alphabetical order (but are shelved by volume number on shelves, 7-15). Miscellaneous material follows in alphabetical order (the archival boxes occupy shelves 16-17).
  Series 1 is stored in special vault facilities. In order to prevent possible delays, researchers should contact the Reference Librarian before visiting.
  Access to the Lewis Carroll photograph albums and the loose Carroll photographs is restricted. See the component record for detail.
  - Subseries 1A: Artwork and Oversize Manuscripts, 1822-1944 August 21; 13 boxes
    Consists of works by individuals such as Wilkie Collins, Alice Pleasance Liddell Hargreaves, and Robert Louis Stevenson, as well as others.
    Not arranged according to any arrangement scheme.
    - Browne, Hablot K., 1836-1863; 1 box
      - charcoal and chalk illustration, "Miss Dinah in deshabille," for Lever's Barrington, 1863; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - charcoal and chalk illustration, "The Major 'departs'--but, not 'in peace,'" for Lever's Barrington, 1863; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - charcoal illustration, "Poaching," for Lever's Barrington, 1863; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - charcoal and chalk illustration, "Not quite the sort of thing--(Aunt Dinah thinks)," for Lever's Barrington, 1863; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - pen-and-ink and wash illustration, "'My good fellow' Said Mr. Winkle extending his hand &c.," for Dickens's Pickwick Papers, 1836-1837; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - pen-and-ink and wash illustration, "I say how nice you look," for Dickens's Pickwick Papers, 1836-37, with photographic negative, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - pencil and chalk illustration of Florence Dombey for Dickens's Dombey and Son, 1846-1848; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - pencil drawing, "Lord Glengariff building a few castles," illustration for Charles Lever's Davenport Dunn, London, 1859, signed "Phiz" [missing as of 4/23/02], dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - colored pencil and watercolor vignette of Mr. Pickwick, signed "Phiz", undated; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - pencil and watercolor vignette of a woman ironing, signed "Phiz", undated; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - engraving, "Hugh & Barnaby Rudge," trial proof of plate for Dickens's Barnaby Rudge, mounted on sheet with watercolor vignette of woman ironing, 1841; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - engraving, "The Marchioness," trial proof of plate for Dickens's Barnaby Rudge, mounted on sheet with watercolor vignette of Mr. Pickwick, 1841; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - watercolor and pencil illustration of the Peckniff family and Tom Pinch for Dickens's Martin Chuzzlewit, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - pen and wash drawing, "Mr. Pickwick in the Fleet," for the Household Edition, p. 337, signed "Phiz", mounted with print of the same drawing, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
      - pen and ink drawing, "Mary Martin's Levee," for Charles Lever's The Martins of Cro 'Martin, 1847, opposite p. 6, signed "Phiz", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 101)
    - Collins, Wilkie, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
      - "Blind Love." Original, autograph manuscript in 15 folders, contained inside an oversize, flat, clamshell case, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 89)
    - Hargreaves, Alice Pleasance Liddell, 1935 January; portion of 1 box
      - Drawing of a mansion. Original painting by Lewis Carroll's "Alice," dated September 14, 1883, and "presented to me [M. L. Parrish] by Caryl Hargreaves, the son of Mrs. Alice Hargreaves, 1935 January." Framed behind glass and contained inside an oversize flat box., 1 box (Box 88)
    - Various Authors, 1874 June 11; 1 folders
      Note: All manuscripts/artwork in this group are either in folders or matted, and contained inside six large clamshell cases (Solander boxes).
      - Charles L. Dodgson's correspondence with J. and E. Kish, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 1)
      - Letter from Lewis Carroll to the Lowrie children (photostat), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 2)
      - "Mathematical Manuscripts" (Dodgson's original envelopes), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 3)
      - "Meeting of [Oxford] Common Room" printed agenda (Dodgson was the Common Room's curator at the time), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 4)
      - Letter with illustrations signed "Charles" [Dodgson] (matted photocopy), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 5)
      - Childhood letter by Robert Louis Stevenson to his parents (matted photocopy; original letter is in Author Files), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 6)
      - The visit of Mr. Charles Kingsley in The Berkeleyan, dated, 1874 June 11; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 7)
      - Publication agreement by George Meredith to write Lord Ormont and his Aminta, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 8)
      - Galley slips of Anthony Trollope's Travel letters nos. 11, 12 and 17, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 9)
      - Autograph manuscript by Thomas Anthony Trollope, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 10)
      - Drafts of Agreement between Ouida (Louise de la Ramée) and Chatto & Windus, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 11)
      - "We are all Ouida's Dogs..." verse by Ouida, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 12)
      - Ouida's "Dog-murder" letter to an editor, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 13)
      - Ouida's "The Dogs of Florence" letter to an editor, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 95, Folder 14)
    - Reade, Charles, 1884 April 22; 3 folders
      - Real estate papers: Brompton Road and other properties, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 96, Folder 1)
      - Real estate papers: Account with Mrs. Matilda Alice Napier (5 Albert Terrace); also for Nos. 2 and 4 Albert Terrace, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 96, Folder 2)
      - Real estate papers: 6 Bolton Row, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 96, Folder 3)
      - Real estate papers: 15 Half Moon Street, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 96, Folder 4)
      - Autograph manuscript of "Nehemiah's Work", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 1)
      - Autograph manuscript of "Reality", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 2)
      - Autograph manuscript of "Monopoly vs. Property", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 3)
      - Autograph manuscript of "Rus", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 4)
      - Autograph manuscript of "Single-heart", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 5)
      - Autograph manuscript of "Suspended Animation", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 6)
      - Autograph manuscript of "The History of a Charity", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 7)
      - Two draft agreements for Double marriage (play), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence relating to John Coleman's production of Reade's play, It's never too late to mend, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 9)
      - Legal documents relating to W. E. Mills' 1863 unauthorized production of Reade's drama, It's never too late to mend, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 10)
      - Agreements concerning a production of Reade's drama, Put yourself in his place, by John Coleman in the United States, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 97, Folder 11)
      - Insurance papers, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 98, Folder 1)
      - Reade vs. Seaman (libel case documents), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 98, Folder 2)
      - Draft of Reade's will dated August 7, 1883, and a letter concerning his estate, 1884 April 22; portion of 1 box (Box 98, Folder 3)
      - Papers written after Reade's death, relating to real estate, etc., dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 98, Folder 4)
    - Hughes Family, 1822-1896; 1 boxes
      - Hughes Family Portraits and Drawings, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99)
      - Watercolor portrait of Thomas Hughes, 1822-1896; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 1)
      - [Hughes Family]. Watercolor of spectators at some event, acquired with a group of drawings by or relating to members of the Hughes family, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 2)
      - Thomas Wilkinson portrait by A. Morton, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 3)
      - A medieval battle scene copied by Gerard Hughes, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 4)
      - Portrait of two girls ("William H. Hughes, Henry S. Hughes" pencilled on back), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 5)
      - Portrait of John Hughes (father of Thomas Hughes) by A. Morton, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 6)
      - John Hughes portrait, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 7)
      - Wilkinson portrait, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 8)
      - "The Age of Innocence" painted by Sir J. Reynolds as drawn by M. Wilkinson ("Margaret E. W. Hughes" pencilled on back), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 9)
      - George Hughes drawn by J. Watkins, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 10)
      - George E. Hughes portrait ("George E. Hughes of Offley Place Eldest brother of Henry Hastings Hughes" pencilled on back), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 11)
      - John Hughes portrait, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 12)
      - "A mountain range, near Rugby, Tennessee," by Sarah J. Hughes, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 13)
      - "A stream, near Rugby, Tennessee," by Sarah J. Hughes, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 14)
      - "Ojai Valley, California" by Sarah J. Hughes, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 15)
      - "Pepper trees" by Sarah J. Hughes, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 99, Folder 16)
    - Various Artists, 1873 April 5-1944 August 21; 1 folders
      - "Story of the Three Sisters": original pen-and-ink sketches by Charles Lutwidge Dodgson (Lewis Carroll) to accompany his adaptation of "The Three Little Pigs" as told to May Mileham, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 1)
      - Pen-and-ink drawing, "As your friend, Rev. Dodgson, I feel bound to point out..." signed by the artist Burr Shafer, reproduced in Saturday Review of Literature, volume XXXI, No. 34 1944 August 21, 21, portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 2)
      - Enlarged photocopy of Lewis Carroll's photograph of Alice Liddell, seated and wearing a wreath on her head, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 3)
      - Enlarged photocopy of Lewis Carroll's photograph of Alice Liddell, seated beside a fern, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 4)
      - Enlarged photocopy of an unsigned drawing after Lewis Carroll's photograph of Alice Liddell, seated beside a fern, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 5)
      - Etching, portrait of Charles Dickens by T. Johnson, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 6)
      - Photograph of Samuel Laurence's portrait of Dickens' character Boz, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 7)
      - Photograph of the cast of No Thoroughfare (a theatrical production co-written by Charles Dickens and Wilkie Collins), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 8)
      - Pen-and-ink drawing of Dickens' "Bob Cratchit and Ebenezer Scrooge" by Harry Furniss, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 9)
      - Pen-and-ink caricature by Harry Furniss of J. M. Barrie smoking a pipe, signed "Celebrities in their old age", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 10)
      - Photograph of J. M. Barrie's mother and two sisters, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 11)
      - Photograph of J. M. Barrie and the cast of an all-star revival of The Admirable Crichton, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 12)
      - Photograph of "J. M. B. leaving the roof of the Wyndhams to write 'Continuation of Rehearsal on Roof of Wyndhams Theatre'", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 13)
      - Pencil study of "Taffy" for "The cut direct" in Trilby by George Du Maurier, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 14)
      - Photograph of Thomas Hardy by Barraud, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 15)
      - Watercolor-and-pencil drawing, "Flowers of Song from Chas. Kingsley's Water Babies," by W. J. Gibbs, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 16)
      - Photograph of Charles Kingsley seated in a chair, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 17)
      - Pencil and wash caricature of Charles Reade signed SEM (Georges Marie Goursat), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 18)
      - Pencil and wash caricature of Anthony Trollope signed SEM (Georges Marie Goursat), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 19)
      - Caricature of Anthony Trollope as published in Vanity Fair (dated ), 1873 April 5; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 20)
      - Pencil portrait of Sir Walter Scott by Francis Alexander, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 21)
      - Pencil and pen-and-ink portrait of Robert Louis Stevenson by Hearth Foley, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 22)
      - Pencil-and-watercolor portrait of W. M. Thackeray's mother, attributed to Samuel Lover, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 100, Folder 23)
    - Reade, Charles, dates not examined; 4 boxes
      - Notecards, dates not examined; 4 boxes (Box 90, Box 91, Box 92, Box 93)
        pproximately 126 large, heavy, stiff cards, roughly 20 x 30 inches in size, with handwritten, miscellaneous notes and references, also some periodical clippings with annotations; some cards bear titles of Reade's works and are not in his hand.
      - "Analysis of the Accounts (Reade and Bentley) Delivered previous to the Injunction" printed on silk cloth. Caption on cardboard frame reads: "Reade refused to allow Bentley to issue cheap editions of Peg Woffington and Christie Johnson. Nevertheless, Bentley did it. Hence the injunction. This is a Special Copy of Bentley's account.", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 103, Folder 1)
      - "Children Should be Either-Handed" printed broadside with an inscription by Reade at the bottom, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 103, Folder 2)
      - Original manuscript of Gold: a true romance. Dramatic story, in two notebooks (pages folded in half and stitched) with autograph note on cover of notebook 2: "part of It is never to late to mend", dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 103, Folder 3)
      - Periodicals and clippings about the "Reade vs. Seaman" libel case, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 103, Folder 4)
    - Stevenson, Robert Louis, dates not examined; 1 box
      - Framed quotation with poem, "My wife and I..." from the library of Robert Louis Stevenson at Vailima (Western Samoa) and Stevenson's home in Edinburgh, Scotland, contained inside a cardboard box, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 102)
    - Various Authors and Artists, 1844 February 26-1937 November 5; 3 folders
      Note: Miscellaneous artwork, illustrations, periodicals, clippings, and other printed materials, either matted or grouped in folders, and contained inside a clamshell case with metal clasps.
      - Certificate of M. L. Parrish's 1939 honorary degree from Princeton University and his membership certificate for The Trollope Society, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 1)
      - Two typewritten poems by J. Kearsley Mitchell (signed "JKM") to M. L. Parrish: "To Morrie, In grateful remembrance of a happy week-end," mounted on a cardboard backing, and a 70th Birthday poem (see Author Files for another poem by Mitchell), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 2)
      - Illustrated Birthday card for M. L. Parrish, addressed "To M. L. Parrish on His 70th Birthday," featuring many signatures, and a matted illustration, featuring M. L. Parrish and the Alice in Wonderland character, inscribed "Happy Birthday to Uncle, Dormy House, ", 1937 November 5; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 3)
      - Alice in Wonderland 100th Anniversary/Pratt Institute Library exhibition poster and an Alice in Wonderland book poster (Knopf), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 4)
      - "Doublets -- a verbal puzzle" by Lewis Carroll for Vanity Fair (March 29, 1879; later published in The Lewis Carroll Handbook, 1979 edition, pp. 102-103), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 5)
      - Poster advertisement (mounted on cardboard) for St. Nicholas, "The Ideal Magazine for Young Folks: The Beautiful Christmas Number" (containing a story by Robert Louis Stevenson, among others), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 6)
      - Original color portrait of Ouida (Louise de la Ramée), matted, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 7)
      - Black and white portrait (reprint) of Ouida, matted, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 8)
      - Illustrated analysis of Wilkie Collins' hands (chiromancy) by Claud Warren, dated, 1881; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 9)
      - Three magazine clippings: "Letters to Eminent Persons. No. LXXII. To Mr. Wilkie Collins" in The World (June 6, 1883); "The Victims of Circumstances" by Wilkie Collins in The Youth's Companion (August 19, 1886); and a short story by Charles Reade, titled "Good Stories of Man and Other Animals," in Harper's Weekly, 1876 June 17; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 10)
      - Set of five old postcards: portrait of "Elizabeth Fry" by G. Richmond and four garden scenes from "Earlham Park." ANS (found loose in box; item association unknown, "1941" pencilled on bottom): "Season's greetings, Dave Randall" (David A. Randall was one of Parrish's many book dealers), dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 11)
      - Map of "Trollope's Barsetshire" inspired by S. Van B. Nichols and painted by George F. Muendel, as published in Yuletide, MCMXXIV, and mounted on cardboard, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 12)
      - Vanity Fair caricature (clipping dated 1873 April 5) of Anthony Trollope with biographical sketch written by Jehu Junior pasted on the back, portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 13)
      - Two caricatures of Thomas Hughes -- one from the July 10, 1872 issue of The Hornet, titled "Master Tom Brown" and matted, and the other from Vanity Fair, dated 1872 June 8, with a biographical opinion written by Jehu Junior pasted on the back, portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 14)
      - Printed leaflets (13) for and (1) against the re-election of Sir Edward Bulwer Lytton as Lord Rector of the University of Glasgow, Scotland, in 1858, as well as four leaflets (mounted on stiff paper) nominating Charles Dickens as Lord Rector by the Committee of Independent Students, portion of 1 box (Box 104, Folder 15)